<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Perspective on seekingfourth</title>
    <link>/categories/perspective/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Perspective on seekingfourth</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 17:43:15 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/perspective/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Right and Wrong</title>
      <link>/posts/right_and_wrong/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 17:43:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/right_and_wrong/</guid>
      <description>Life keeps presenting choices in front of us, and we have to make one every time. It is an interesting thing that everyone makes the right choice, and does the right thing. No? Yes. You will also hear statements like &amp;#34;I am doing this wrong…&amp;#34; because &amp;#34;it is the right thing to do at this moment&amp;#34;. Basically, our inner instrument justifies the righteousness of our wrong action. But, such statements remain in the projected light of one&amp;#39;s own knowledge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do you desire yourself?</title>
      <link>/posts/do_you_desire_yourself/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 13:08:38 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/do_you_desire_yourself/</guid>
      <description>Whatever a human achieves, is through concentration of mind and a developed intellect which can discriminate and will. It is very well known that a calm mind achieves more than an agitated mind. A personality living the agitations is tossed here and there with the compulsions of the acquired nature. Agitations are caused by attachments primarily, which subsequently leads to fear and anger. Fear is of losing the object of attachment and anger arises for anything which comes in the way of you and the object.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science, Technology and Deployment</title>
      <link>/posts/science_technology_deployment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 12:56:39 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/science_technology_deployment/</guid>
      <description>Wonderment, Curiosity and Necessity have propelled humans to explore and invent. In untiring joy of experiments and/or a goal in mind, a Scientist brings forth some scientific truth. Based on this scientific discovery, Engineers workout a technology which goes further through the ecosystem and becomes a product in service of beings. Entire cycle goes through continuous improvements so that it can become easily accessible for the masses - better and efficient.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women are Spiritually advanced</title>
      <link>/posts/women_are_spiritually_advanced/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 17:53:59 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/women_are_spiritually_advanced/</guid>
      <description>I find that Women are spiritually advanced naturally, which means they are positioned at an advanced stage of human evolution. This assertion is not just a sentimental thought but logically true for three primary reasons:
Intuition  You would agree that women are relatively more intuitive. When we think logically, our &amp;#34;I&amp;#34; thought rises and arranges several other thoughts, do calculations and decide what to do. What we tend to forget that &amp;#34;I&amp;#34; is yet another thought or when becomes decisive, it is an individual will, but still, it is also powered by some other energy which is the very source of our existence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I am</title>
      <link>/posts/i_am/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 17:15:35 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/i_am/</guid>
      <description>Now, you are looking for I am…what?
 When we are born, we are stamped with some identities. Then we start accumulating memories and more identities. Kid…memories of being kid, student…memories of being student, son/daughter, brother/sister, friend/foe, profession, father/mother and many. What we do is that we presume some identity and we work to make it strong. To make it strong, we need evidence and we need more of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy New Year</title>
      <link>/posts/happy_new_year/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 13:39:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/happy_new_year/</guid>
      <description>You would be joyful today, wouldn’t you? Why not, it’s about to be new year! You will refresh yourself by loosen up your (bad) memories of past and will be more determined with the plans for new year. Fantastic!
 The breeze of new year will keep you on your toes for some days or a month and then you will start losing the excitement. Sounds familiar? Happened in past as well?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We all are Travellers</title>
      <link>/posts/all_travellers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 13:23:12 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/all_travellers/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever noticed that all of us know(consciously or unconsciously) that we are not just the body but we are something more? Have you paid attention to statements like “I am having a body ache!”. Who is having the body ache? If you are not just the body, who are you then? We satisfy our intellect by trying to know so many things. But, does it ever get satisfied?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are you doing with your seed?</title>
      <link>/posts/seed/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 13:14:17 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/seed/</guid>
      <description>Last week, there was a surprise visit from a religious group in my locality. They sang religious songs, chanted God’s name(s) and most of the people joined. It was very harmonical. At last, we were discussing one of the “shlokas” from The Gita, which briefly meant, God comes from time to time to establish “dharma” on earth. Some believe it, some don’t. Suppose this is true. Suppose the God will come after 1000years from now.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
