<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vedānta on seekingfourth - That Alone is Truth</title>
    <link>/categories/ved%C4%81nta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vedānta on seekingfourth - That Alone is Truth</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 16:06:06 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/ved%C4%81nta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Spirituality-108: Under the light of Vedānta</title>
      <link>/post/spirituality108/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 16:06:06 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/spirituality108/</guid>
      <description>Peace chant  ॐ सह नाववतु सह नौ भुनक्तु । सह वीर्यं करवावहै तेजस्वि नावधीतमस्तु मा विद्विषावहै । ॐ शान्तिः शान्तिः शान्तिः ॥   Om, May Brahman protect us both! May Brahman bestow upon us both the fruit of knowledge! May we both obtain the energy to acquire knowledge! May what we both study reveal the Truth! May we cherish no ill feeling toward each other! Om. Peace! Peace!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steps to Self Realization</title>
      <link>/post/steps_to_self/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 07:17:29 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/steps_to_self/</guid>
      <description>ādiŚankara in aparokṣānūbhūti describes 15 steps to direct realization of ātman (Self, Consciousness, Brahman). This article lists them briefly along with guidance available from other revered texts. For detailed study, please see References at the end.
1. yamḥ - The purification of the Senses   The restraint of all the senses by means of such knowledge as &amp;#34;All this is Brahman&amp;#34; is called yamḥ
 From Yogasūtra, it consists of:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vedānta</title>
      <link>/post/vedanta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2021 14:01:38 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/vedanta/</guid>
      <description> Introduction  Vedānta is combination of two words: Veda means Knowledge and anta means end. So, it means end of knowledge.
 This is not pessimistic end of knowledge, it means a state where there is nothing more to be known.
 Since the end portions of Vedas, talk and provide instructions to attain such state, they are also called Vedānta.
 Article in progress…
   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Reality and in Goodness</title>
      <link>/post/in_reality_and_in_goodness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 11:27:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/in_reality_and_in_goodness/</guid>
      <description>We know, we live in a world of cause and effect. So, each of our actions causes some effects on the world and on us. Whatever actions we perform, they leave residues in our mind. If we receive happiness from some action, we want more of it or fear the absence of it. On the other hand, if it is grief, we want to run away from it. These residues build our tendencies, make our world of likes and dislikes, and propel us to act further putting us in a vicious cycle of cause and effect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Om Shāntih Shāntih Shāntih</title>
      <link>/post/om_shantih/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 18:15:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/om_shantih/</guid>
      <description>ॐ शांतिः शांतिः शांतिः ।। (Om! Peace! Peace! Peace!)
 Everybody wants peace, not for idleness but for activity too. Without peace, life would be at constant war externally and internally. It can&amp;#39;t make any progressive development. However, it has become such a rare phenomenon that people have actually started considering it as an ultimate goal in life:
 Peace is not the ultimate goal, but the most fundamental requirement in one’s life.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
